A Guide to the Pearl M. Brickman Architectural Collection, 1977-2002
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Pearl M. Brickman Architectural Collection, 1977-2002
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2013-081
6.2 cu. ft. 1 Box; 12 oversized folders.
Pearl Brickman (1928- ). Collection includes three design projects she developed during her years (1977-1979) at Southern California Institute of Architecture (SCI Arc), and fifteen projects from her professional career (1982-2002), including project descriptions, drawings,and progress photographs.
Brickman, Pearl M.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Pearl M. Brickman Architectural Collection was donated to the International Archive of Women in Architecture by the creator in 2012.
Biographical Note
Pearl M. Brickman was a double major in art and education at Brooklyn College. After graduation, she moved to Los Angeles, CA and worked as an elementary art teacher. At the age of 46 she decided to go back to school and get a Master in Architecture at Southern California Institute of Architecture (SCI-Arc). After working for a year in two different offices, she opened her own firm and worked as an architect for 25 years focusing primarily on residential remodels.
Scope and Content Note
The collection includes three design projects she developed during her years in SCI Arc, including her thesis. Also present are 15 projects from her professional career ranging from 1982 to 2002. Each project has a series of hand drawn plans, sections and detail drawings. Some projects contain photographs.
Index Terms
Persons:
Gottlieb, Lois Davidson
Genre and Form Terms:
Architectural drawings.
Occupations:
Architects.
Subjects:
Architecture; International Archive of Women in Architecture (IAWA); Women-owned architectural firms.
Contents List
- Brief Biography,1986-2004, undated (Box-folder 1-1)
- Student Work,1977-1979
  - Schoolwork Portfolio,1977-1979 (Box-folder 1-2)
    Scope and Content
    Includes additions to Gottlieb House, 2228 Senecia, Los Angeles. See also Lois Davidson Gottlieb Architectural Collection, Ms1997-003.
  - SCI-Arc coursework, Second Year Study,1977 (Oversize Map Case 35/Drawer 13/Folder 9)
  - SCI-Arc coursework, High Tech House and Louis Khan Inspiration House,1977 (Oversize Map Case 35/Drawer 13/Folder 8)
  - SCI-Arc coursework, Center of Contemporary Expression (Thesis),1978 (Oversize Map Case 35/Drawer 13/Folder 10)
- Office Records,1983-1989, undated (Box-folder 1-3)
- Women + Architecture Statewide Conference, San Diego, CA, Conference Handbook,1990 (Box-folder 1-12)
- Project Records,1984-2002
  - Project Descriptions,undated (Box-folder 1-4)
  - Sosner House (Sherman Oaks, CA),1982 (Oversize Map Case 35/Drawer 13/Folder 7)
  - Center for Law in Public Interest (CLIPI) (Los Angeles, CA),1983-1985 (Box-folder 1-9, Oversize Map Case 35/Drawer 13/Folder 6)
  - Frandzel House (Sherman Oaks, CA),1983-1989 (Oversize Map Case 35/Drawer 13/Folder 5, Box-folder 1-5)
  - Wetzler House, 1983-1984 (Oversize Map Case 35/ Drawer 13/ Folder 7)
  - Beery House (Sherman Oaks, CA),1984-1986 (Box-folder 1-8, Oversize Map Case 35/Drawer 13/Folder 3)
  - Robbins House (Beverly Hills, CA),1985 (Box-folder 1-6, Oversize Map Case 35/Drawer 13/Folder 6)
  - Resch Residence (Beverly Hills, CA),1986-1995 (Box-folder 1-7, Oversize Map Case 35/Drawer 13/Folder 4)
  - Whitney/Balmagia (Santa Monica, CA), 1987 (Oversize Map Case 35/Drawer 13/Folder 3)
  - Metzger House (Santa Monica, CA),1989 (Oversize Map Case 35/Drawer 13/Folder 7)
  - UCLA Daily Bruin and KLA Radio (Los Angeles, CA),1989-1990 (Oversize Map Case 35/Drawer 13/Folder 2)
  - Guest House (Los Angeles, CA),1990-1991 (Oversize Map Case 35/Drawer 13/Folder 2)
  - Bacal House (Los Angeles, CA), 1997 (Oversize Map Case 35/Drawer 13/Folder 1)
  - Singer House,1997 (Oversize Map Case 35/Drawer 13/Folder 1)
  - Blavin House (Los Angeles, CA),2002 (Oversize Map Case 35/Drawer 13/Folder 1)
  - Inadomi House,2002 (Box-folder 1-10, Oversize Map Case 35/Drawer 13/Folder 12)
  - Three Kitchen Designs, (includes Metzler Kitchen), 2002 (Box-folder 1-11, Oversize Map Case 35/Drawer 13/Folder 11)
  - Ward Kitchen Remodel (Santa Monica, CA),2002 (Oversize Map Case 35/Drawer 13/Folder 11)